The new king of AI coding is here.
Anthropic just released Claude Sonnet
4.5 and it is looking really really
good. I know that benchmarks don't tell
us the entire story, but right now
Sonnet 4.5 is at the top of the charts
even beating out previous Anthropic
models like Opus 4.1 and it is
apparently better than GPT-5 Codex for
OpenAI which has been absolutely
crushing it recently. Now the big
question is is it actually better in
practice? So I'm going to be testing
live with you in this video building out
the exact same implementation with both
Sonnet 4.5 and Claude Code and GPT-5
Codex in Codex. So more on that a little
bit. Really excited for that. And then
for our other benchmarks, Sonnet 4.5 is
now leading in agentic tool use and
compared to Opus 4.1, we have some
massive strides in computer use almost a
20% jump which is really exciting.
Definitely a lot more with computer use
coming in the near future here.
Now we also have the official Claude
Code version 2.0. So a lot of
improvements they've made with Claude
Code of course being powered by Sonnet
4.5 by default now and you can still
switch to the old Opus 4.1 if you want.
They also added a VS Code extension and
they've been making improvements to
their Claude Code SDK which are now
calling the Claude Agents SDK. So if you
want to build a custom agentic
experiences using Claude Code, this is
the ticket for you. So yeah, a lot of
improvements that they've been making
across the board and Anthropic has been
pumping out a ton of content on their
YouTube channel today. So they're going
hard with their new Sonnet 4.5. And so
with that, let's actually do a test
here. I want to see how Sonnet 4.5
compares to GPT-5 Codex when working on
a new feature in an existing complex
code base. All right, take a look at
this. On the left side, I've got Codex
running with a GPT-5 Codex for the LLM
and then for Claude Code on the right
hand side, I'm running the shiny new
Sonnet 4.5.
And I'm actually really curious what the
results of this test is because I'm
running this live with you. I did not do
a dry run of this and a lot of people
have been switching over to Codex from
Claude Code. And so I'm really curious
if Sonnet 4.5 is enough to bring
everyone back. And I know that one
single test really isn't enough to tell,
but I'm just trying to get my feet wet
here with you seeing what kind of
results that we get executing on the
exact same requirements document that I
have to build a Stripe integration into
an existing agentic application. And so
this is one of the applications that I
have built out for the Dynamis
community. It's a chat GPT-like
interface to talk to a rag agent behind
the scenes. I'm just giving a really
simple demo here and I already have the
Stripe integration built out in a
different branch in Git, but yeah, we
can buy our tokens here. So I can go in
and enter in fake credit card
information cuz this is just using the
Stripe test account here. So I thought
this is just going to be a really nice
demo for comparing our two models now.
So I'll go ahead and buy some tokens
here just so you can see how this works
exactly. I can go to my chat here and
now I have my updated token balance and
then when I send in another message, it
deducts the tokens automatically. So
this is like a little overview of what
we're looking to build here with both
Claude Code and Codex. And I picked this
use case specifically because it's not
trivial, but it's also not going to take
two hours for this implementation to
complete. It's the perfect balance here
where generally I've seen Claude Sonnet
4 mess up on the little things, but
still mostly get it right. And so we can
see how that compares now with GPT-5
Codex and Sonnet 4.5. So without further
ado, let's go ahead and kick off the
instruction set for both of our coding
agents. And so they're both working on a
different version of the repository. So
they're not stepping on each other's
toes and also they're working on
something that is pre-Stripe
integration. So this is the goal that
we're working towards that I demoed
earlier. They're working on a code base
that doesn't have this whole thing set
up yet. So we'll go ahead and see how
they perform. And I'll just show you
really quickly the instruction set
they're working with here. So I've
showed PRPs on my channel before. It's
basically just a structured approach to
define our AI coding workflow. And so
the command that we just executed, it's
going to load our feature requirement,
think through the implementation, break
it down into tasks and then handle that
task by task. That's what we're
executing right now in both Codex and
Claude Code. And so I'll pull up both of
these again. I'll go ahead and pause the
video and then come back once we have
the first attempt for both of our coding
agents and we'll see the results. All
right, I'm back mid-execution cuz I want
to show you how things are going in
Claude Code and Codex while we are in
the middle of building the application.
So we got Codex on the left hand side
doing a lot of stuff with the database
right now. It is failing to run a lot of
these commands which is not looking the
best for Codex and it's a lot slower to
do things like read through my files in
general. Claude Sonnet 4.5 on the other
hand has been blazing through this
implementation. Now in the end, what
matters the most is code quality, but
speed is nice as well and it definitely
seems like Sonnet is really really fast
especially with new 4.5. And then going
into Arkon here, we can see the task
list for both Codex and Claude Code.
Claude has gotten through quite a bit
already. So it just finished the front
end purchase components for Stripe for
the tokens. Now it's working on the
display components. And then Codex, they
just finished the database schema
changes now working on some of the back
end stuff with Stripe. So they're both
chugging along pretty well. Definitely a
difference in speed though here. So I'll
come back again once we have the full
implementation. We'll see who knocked it
out of the park the best. There we go.
Claude Code with Sonnet 4.5 has finished
the implementation and it did it in 15
minutes. The entire Stripe
implementation. It was very very
impressive. I actually did this exact
same build with Opus 4.1 in the past 35
minutes to build the whole thing. So
more than two times faster now with 4.5.
Now I verified the output before I even
ran anything. I knew it made a couple of
mistakes just small things with the URLs
between the front end and the back end.
So I had to correct that. So it wasn't
quite a one-shot, but it was really
really close. So I set up my environment
and restarted my containers here. So now
we have the same application that we saw
earlier, but instead of the previous one
that I built with Opus 4.1, this is the
version now built with Sonnet 4.5. Take
a look at this. The UI is pretty nice.
Maybe it could be a little bit better in
the top right here, but still pretty
good. I send in a message. I don't have
any tokens yet. Please purchase more to
continue. So I'll go ahead and buy some
tokens and instead of buying in line, it
actually brings me to a Stripe checkout
here. I don't really know which one's
necessarily better, but I mean this is
certainly a good implementation as well.
So I have my test Stripe running here.
So I'll just go ahead and enter in some
fake credit card information again.
Have to enter in a little bit more cuz
it's a checkout here. There we go. All
right, pay for my tokens in the sandbox
environment and boom, there we go.
Current tokens 250. Go back to chatting
and now I'll send in a message just
hello for a quick test and see if we get
a response. There we go. All right, how
can I assist you today? It looks like
the token count did not update though.
So if I refresh my page, now goes to 49.
So a little bit of an issue there. Looks
like I just have to iterate one more
time to make everything perfect, but
yeah, that's just two iterations and we
have this full Stripe integration built
into Claude Code. And meanwhile,
Codex is still going this entire time.
As I did some updates even like fix up
the URLs and stuff, Codex has been going
for over a half hour now. And so I'm
going to pause again and come back once
Codex is done, but so far it's really
really disappointing me. Actually, it
looks like it's been going for almost an
hour now because I gave it a lot of
time. I took a break in between Claude
being done and me doing these little
fixes here and re-recording this. And so
yeah, it's been going on for over an
hour. So Codex seems pretty
disappointing here. Sonnet 4.5 is doing
a really good job. All right, I finally
got Codex to finish. It took 1 hour and
20 minutes in total for the
implementation while Sonnet 4.5 took 15
minutes. So the speed pretty
disappointing. It seemed to do a lot of
weird things where like after it would
edit a file, it would reread the file to
make sure the changes were made. Things
like that that again might be specific
to Codex running on Windows, but I
really wasn't happy with that. So
anyway, I did the same thing with Claude
Code where I gave it a couple of
chances. I iterated a couple of times
with some similar issues it had around
environment setup this time more with
some Docker things specifically. So I
got that all squared away. I have the
containers running in Codex again and so
let's go back over to the site and take
a look at what we got. So first thing
that I noticed, the UI isn't quite as
nice. I mean, it'd be easy to fix that.
So that's totally fine. Let's see if we
can purchase our tokens. So purchase
tokens. Okay, looking really good. And
we even have a token history. Doesn't
seem to be perfect here,
but it's definitely cool that we have
that. So let's go ahead. I'll purchase
$20 worth of tokens here. I'll select
this and okay, nice. I think I do
actually prefer this than going to a
separate checkout page. So so far, the
actual results with using Codex is
pretty good. I hate how long I had to
wait, but I mean it did a pretty good
job with the implementation. Things
aren't perfect yet like the transaction
history in the UI, but it's still pretty
solid. Yeah, there we go. Payment
successful. We have 600 tokens. The
current balance isn't quite right cuz
that's actually my old balance. So
things to be improved here, but yeah,
our token balance is updated. I can send
in a message here and it'll deduct a
token from our agent. I might have to
refresh the page for it to refresh here.
Okay, so yeah, not quite perfect there
either. So, there's like three or four
issues that we have to fix here. So, not
quite as good of an implementation as
Claude Code. This is why this is the
perfect use case cuz it's not trivial.
We see these problems as it messes up on
things, but also like it does a good
enough job where we can have a full
presentation demonstrating the mistakes
versus just the application crashing,
right? So, yeah, this is pretty good.
And I can go in and reset my tokens down
to zero and we can make sure that we are
not able to send a message. Yep, okay.
So, this is working really good. So,
overall, I would say that Claude Sonnet
4.5 was faster by a lot and better by a
decent amount. Codex is still really
solid and I do think that we're going to
get to a point really quick where it
will catch up to Claude Code. However,
with Sonnet 4.5, they're definitely
winning the race right now. So, I hope
that you found this comparison
interesting, very exciting what we've
got going on happening right now with a
Sonnet 4.5 continuing to push the LLM
race further. So, if you appreciated
this video, you're looking forward to
more things on large language models and
building agents and AI coding, I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next video.